Cristóbal Sifón

Profesor Asociado Instituto de Física, Facultad de Ciencias Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso Casilla 4059, Valparaíso, Chile

Phone: +56 (32) 227 4698 http://fis.ucv.cl/cristobal-sifon/ https://github.com/cristobal-sifon/

E-mail: cristobal.sifon@pucv.cl

Research Interests

My research focuses on galaxy cluster physics including observable—mass scaling relations for cosmological analyses, brightest cluster galaxies, the mass content of cluster galaxies, and merging clusters. I am also interested in intrinsic galaxy alignments, both as contaminants for cosmic shear and as a physical mechanism in their own right. I use various tools and techniques to study these phenomena, including weak gravitational lensing, spectroscopy, the exploitation of optical surveys in general, and most recently analyses involving hydrodynamical simulations.

Collaborations: Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) — Canadian Cluster Comparison Project (CCCP) — Galaxy Cluster Mass Reconstruction Project — Kilo-Degree Survey (KiDS) — Large Synoptic Survey Telescope Dark Energy Science Collaboration (LSST-DESC) — Multi-Epoch Nearby Cluster Survey (MENeaCS) — Simons Observatory.

Employment

[2019 - Present] Profesor Asociado (Assistant Professor), Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso (PUCV), Chile

[2016 - 2019] Postdoctoral Research Associate, Princeton University, USA

Education

[2012 - 2016] Ph.D. Astrophysics, Universiteit Leiden, The Netherlands

[2010 - 2012] M.Sc. Astrophysics, P. Universidad Católica de Chile (PUC), Chile

[2005 - 2010] B.Sc. Astronomy, P. Universidad Católica de Chile, Chile

Internships

[2011] Science Intern, Gemini South Observatory (6 months)

[2011] Internship, Rutgers University (2 months)

[2009] Science Intern, Gemini South Observatory (6 months, B.Sc. thesis)

Teaching & Mentoring

Student Research Mentoring

[2020 - present] Camila Aros, PUCV: MSc thesis advisor.

[2020 – present] Nicole Mejía, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de Honduras (Honduras): Advising undergraduate research project through the Central American-Caribbean Bridge in Astrophysics Program.

[2017 - 2019] Naomi Robertson, Oxford University (UK): co-advised PhD thesis project.

[2018] Malik Walker, Princeton University: Undegraduate Summer Research Program and Junior Project.

[2013 – 2014] Joshua Albert, Universiteit Leiden: co-advised MSc thesis project.

Courses Taught

[2020B] Observational Cosmology (graduate level, PUCV)

Teaching Assistant

[Leiden] Stellar dynamics; organizer of MSc thesis defense presentations

[PUC] Extragalactic astrophysics; Experimental astrophysics; Laboratory of thermodynamics and kinetic theory

Grants

[2019] Proyecto FONDECYT Iniciación (PI, 3 years, US\$125,000)

Successful Observing Proposals (as PI)

I have been the PI of 9 different successful observing proposals in 5 different telescopes:

[Magellan/FourStar] (2020AB,2019AB) 6 nights for near-infrared imaging of galaxy clusters

[Very Large Array] (2019A) 4.5 h to study AGN feedback in galaxy clusters

[Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope] (2017B,2013B) 44 h to study diffuse radio emission in clusters

[Gemini South/GMOS] (2017B) 24 h for optical imaging and spectroscopy of high-redshift galaxy clusters

[VLT Survey Telescope/OmegaCAM] (2015A) 6 h for optical imaging of galaxy clusters

Observing Experience: I have spent roughly 180 hours observing with optical (Gemini South/GMOS) and near-infrared (NTT/Sofl, Magellan/Fourstar) instruments performing both imaging and spectroscopy of galaxy clusters.

Community Activity

Journals: I have served as a referee for Astronomy & Astrophysics, The Astrophysical Journal, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, and Nature Astronomy.

Telescope Allocation Committees (TACs): I have served as a reviewer for the Canadian TAC, as well as for the *Chandra* X-ray Observatory.

Informal courses

[2016] Making Better Figures, Universiteit Leiden (http://bit.ly/2NTznxW)

Press articles authored

Galaxy clusters: Falling into line (Nature Astronomy News & Views, July 2017)

Dynamical masses of galaxy clusters discovered with the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect (Gemini Focus Featured Science, July 2013)

Outreach

[2018 - 2019] Assisted with Public Astronomical Observations in Spanish, Princeton University.

[2013 - 2014] Assisted with Public Observations at the Old Observatory, Leiden Observatory.

[2012] Co-taught an Astronomy Course for Seniors, PUC.

[2011] Participated in *Starry Nights*, observation nights for elementary and middle school students in social risk organized by ESO-Santiago.

[2010] Invited talk on board the "FFG14 Almirante Latorre" Chilean Navy ship, Valparaíso, Chile.

[2010] The Universe, a series of talks for elementary school students in social risk organized by PUC.

Technical skills

I am an experienced python programmer, and I also have some experience with IRAF/PyRAF. I have written pygmos, a Python/PyRAF pipeline to reduce Gemini-GMOS spectra which is available here. I also developed an early analysis pipeline for the FLAMINGOS-II infrared imager and spectrograph installed in the Gemini-South telescope. I am one of three lead developers and maintainers of the galaxy-galaxy lensing pipeline used by the

KiDS collaboration (written in python, but which is not public at the moment). Other codes I have written are posted at my github page.

Other Work Experience

[2007 – 2008] Ski instructor at Homewood Mountain Ski Resort in Lake Tahoe, CA. Obtained certification as Level I Ski Instructor by the Professional Ski Instructors of America (PSIA).

[2006 – 2007] Ski lift operator at Sun Valley Resort, Sun Valley, ID.

References

Prof. Henk Hoekstra (*PhD advisor*)
 Leiden Observatory, Universiteit Leiden
 Niels Bohrweg 2, NL-2333 CA Leiden, The Netherlands
 Phone: +31 (71) 527 5594

E-mail: hoekstra@strw.leidenuniv.nl

 Prof. David N. Spergel Center for Computational Astrophysics, Flatiron Institute 160 Fifth Avenue, 7th Floor, New York, NY 10010, USA

Phone: +1 (646) 654 0066

E-mail: dns@astro.princeton.edu

Prof. John P. Hughes
 Department of Physics and Astronomy, Rutgers University
 136 Frelinghuysen Rd., Piscataway, NJ 08854, USA
 Phone: +1 (848) 445 8878

E-mail: jph@physics.rutgers.edu

Prof. L. Felipe Barrientos (MSc advisor)
 Instituto de Astrofísica, P. Universidad Católica de Chile
 Casilla 306, Santiago 22, Chile
 Phone: +56 (2) 2354 4941

E-mail: barrientos@astro.uc.cl

Prof. Felipe Menanteau
 Department of Astronomy, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
 1002 W. Green St., Urbana, IL 61801, USA

Phone: +1 (217) 244 6297 E-mail: felipe@illinois.edu